Email: singh.gurbaj5124871@gmail.com Website: https://workspace.gurbaj.dev

LinkedIn: linkedin.com/in/gurbaj-singh-b64198b5

Github: <u>github.com/gurbaj5124871</u> Contact: +91-7973025869

GURBAJ SINGH

INTRO

I am a senior software engineer with experience of working in various product based companies of about 7+ years specialising in backend development, system architecture, DevOps, and data engineering. Machine learning and blockchain enthusiast. My expertise extends to designing and implementing scalable solutions, leading teams, mentoring engineers and driving innovation.

SKILLS

- Programming Languages: Go, Typescript/Javascript, Python
- Platforms/Frameworks: NodeJS (nestJS, expressJS, apollo/graphql), Go
 (Gin), Python (fastAPI, flask, asyncio)
- Databases: PostgreSQL, MongoDB, MySQL, Cassandara, DynamoDB, Neo4J
- Caching Stores: Redis Standalone/Clustered, Apache Ignite
- Message Brokers: Apache Kafka, RabbitMQ, AWS SQS
- Search Engines: Elasticsearch, Milvus (Vector Store)
- Data Warehouses: AWS Redshift, Clickhouse
- Real Time Application Technologies: MQTT, TCP/WS, gRPC, RTMP
- Containerisation and Orchestration: Docker, Docker Swarm, Kubernetes
- Cloud Platforms: AWS, GCP, DigitalOcean
- ML/AI: OpenAI(gpt, whisper), Deepseek-r1, LLaMA, tensorflow, PyTorch

EXPERIENCE

Range.org - Switzerland/Remote - Senior Backend Engineer

Aug 2023 - PRESENT

A Monitoring, Threat Prevention, Forensics and Compliance Platform for Blockchains specialising in Cosmos and Solana ecosystem.

- Designed and developed a Monitoring System pipeline that executes user-created alert rules via a dashboard or SDK, enabled real-time notifications with 99.9% uptime using Go, Postgres, Kafka, NodeJS, Typescript(for SDK).
- The system scales horizontally to accommodate 100 million plus transactions per day, ensuring resilience and fault tolerance, with an end-to-end execution time averaging 400 milliseconds per block.
- Spearheaded **multi-node Kubernetes cluster** setup and CI/CD pipeline for high-availability deployments using Github Actions and Ansible.
- Built a Forensics product that enables security auditors to track and visualise transaction flows from funding source to destination using Neo4j graph database.

- Worked on a Sybil Detection Data Science project using heuristics such as
 Direct Address Reuse (DAR) to group Externally Owned Addresses by
 identifying centralised exchange addresses from large blockchain
 datasets, aiding in the successful execution of confidential chain
 airdrop. Published the white paper on the heuristics used and learnings.
- Built and maintained the **open-source SDK** for custom user-hosted alert rules, ensuring seamless security and usability
- Integrated multiple chains into the platform like Solana, Cosmoshub, Osmosis, Celestia, dYdX, Noble, Stride, Provenance etc.

Rumi (formerly Waitroom) - USA/Remote - Senior Software Engineer

Sep 2020 - Aug 2023

An AI enhanced video meeting platform for smart and streamlined meetings.

- Architected a highly secure **Authentication** and **Authorization** service using **Go (Gin) and Casbin**, supporting policy-based RBAC.
- Designed users and meetings service using NodeJS (Typescript/NestJS),
 PostgreSQL, DynamoDB and Redis
- Developed catchup feature which summarises meetings in real time from real time translations using LLM (gpt-4), Python (Fastapi, asyncio)
- Designed and built **Recording service** to record live meetings in both landscape and portrait format, **transcoded** in various formats using **ffmpeg**
- Extended recording pipeline to generate clips using computer vision
- Designed and built RAG (Retrieval-Augmented Generation) feature on transcriptions from meetings using milvus and LLM (gpt-4).
- Designed and build **real time streaming data pipelines** using **Apache Kafka** to collect engagement metrics for real time analytics
- Designed and built data warehouse using AWS Redshift to ingest heavy real time streams of data and processed into different tables for faster reads
- Led **backend engineer hiring**, including technical interviews and assignment evaluations, contributing to the growth of a high-performing team.

Accelerator App - Canada/Remote - Software Engineer

Sep 2019 - Aug 2020

A platform for incubators to manage their startups with tools/features like applications, coaching, metrics etc.

- Migrated backend systems from Javascript to Typescript and REST to GraphQL (ApolloJS), reducing response times by 30% and improving developer productivity.
- Implemented scalable search and filtering capabilities for large datasets using Elasticsearch, supporting incubators in managing applications.
- Integrated third-party calendar systems (Google and Microsoft Calendar) to enhance scheduling features.
- Built Real Time chat based on web sockets to provide group discussions.
- Introduced and contributed to Unit Tests, Integration Tests and End to End tests using Jest, cypress and mocked dependency injections.
- Built CI/CD which would ensure build and test coverage status checks before deployments.

Dextra, New Delhi - Backend and Devops Engineer

Aug 2018 - Aug 2019

A social media platform for different types of artists to find and collaborate with each other

- Converted The monolithic to microservices architecture to have higher availability and horizontal scalability.
- Built Real Time Chat supporting direct and group conversations using MQTT(realtime lightweight protocol for IoT) and Cassandra DB (Highly available and Partition tolerant with tunable consistency).
- Implemented the social/graph aware semantic search engine using Elasticsearch with creating the highly scalable architecture having multiple shards for multiple indexes with multiple nodes and replicas.
- Build cached feeds for users to consume artists content using Redis.
- Transitioned the whole server architecture's domain from Dextra.art to Dextra.com.
- Wrote Mails automation platform for marketing team which could send bulk emails from their personal gmail account or mailgun with unsubscribe functionality.

Jungleworks, Chandigarh - Backend Developer

July 2017 - July 2018

Service based company, worked with clients from all over the world like usa, japan etc

- Responsible for the backend of the projects (scratch and retainers) implemented on nodeJS with databases like mongoDB/mySQL/postgreSQL.
- Worked on the base project for the company following the microservices architecture which was later used by other members of the company to use it as base with standards to implement projects faster.
- Worked on very tight deadline projects with penalty clauses.
- Have experience in working with oversea clients over calls.

Jungleworks, Chandigarh — Backend Intern

Jan 2017 - June 2017

- As an intern with no mentor started working on live projects with full responsibility on backend of the project
- Worked in parallel on two projects one with full backend responsibility and another with tech lead.
- Build base by learning javascript/nodeJS and databases like mongoDB

EDUCATION

Chitkara University, India - Bachelors of Engineering in ECE

June 2013 - June 2017, Baddi, HP